I'd like to welcome you to
this course on computer science.
Actually, it's a terrible way to start.
Computer science
is a terrible name for this business.
First of all it's not a science.
It might be engineering...
or it might be art...
Or we'll actually see that computer...
so-called 'science'
actually has a lot in common with magic.
We will see that in this course.
So it's not a science. It's also
not really very much about computers.
And it's not about computers
in the same sense that...
that physics is not really
about particle accelerators...
and biology is not really
about microscopes and Petri dishes.
and it's not about computers
in the same sense that geometry
is not really about
using surveying instruments.
In fact there is a lot of commonality
between computer science and geometry.
Geometry first of all
is another subject with a lousy name.
The name comes from 'Gaia' meaning
the earth and 'Metron' meaning to measure.
Geometry originally meant
measuring the earth... or surveying.
And the reason for that was
that thousands of years ago
the Egyptian priesthood
developed rudiments of geometry
in order to figure out how to restore the
boundaries of fields that were destroyed
in the annual flooding of the Nile.
And to the Egyptians who did that
the geometry really was
the use of surveying instruments.
Now, the reason that we think that
computer science is about computers
is pretty much the same reason
that the Egyptians thought geometry
was about surveying instruments.
and that is when
some field is just getting started and
you don't really understand it very well
it's very easy to confuse
the essence of what you're doing
with the tools that you use.
And indeed on some absolute
scale of things we probably know less
about the essence of computer science
than the ancient Egyptians
really knew about geometry.
Well, what I mean
by the essence of computer science,
what I mean by the essence of geometry...
See, it's certainly true that these
Egyptians often used surveying instruments.
But when we look back on them
after a couple of thousands years we say
"Gee! What they were doing?"
The important stuff they were doing
was to begin to formalize
notions about space and time.
To start a way of talking about...
mathematical truth formally that led
to the axiomatic method, that led to...
sort of all of modern mathematics.
Figuring out a way to talk precisely
about so-called 'declarative' knowledge -
'what is true'.
Well, similarly, I think in the future
people will look back and say,
yes, those
primitives in the twentieth century
were fiddling around
with these gadgets called computers,
but really what they were doing
is starting to learn how to formalize...
formalize intuitions about... process...
how to do things.
Starting to develop a way...
to talk precisely
about 'how to' knowledge,
as opposed to geometry
that talks about 'what is true'.
Let me give you an example of that.
Let's take a look... Here is
a piece of... a piece of mathematics.
Right? That says what a square root is.
The square root of X is the number Y
such that Y squared is equal to X
and Y is greater than zero.
Now that's a fine piece of mathematics,
but just telling you what a square root
is doesn't really say anything about...
about
how you might go out and find one.
Let's contrast that
with a piece of imperative knowledge.
Right? How you might
go out and find the square root.
This in fact also comes from Egypt.
Not ancient-ancient Egypt.
This is an algorithm
due to Heron of Alexandria
called how to find a square root
by successive averaging.
And what it says is...
That in order to find a square root...
... in order to find a square root
you make a guess,
you improve that guess,
and the way you improve the guess is to
average the guess and X over the guess
(we'll talk a little bit later
why that's a reasonable thing)
and you keep improving
the guess until it's good enough.
That's a method.
That's how to do something.
As opposed to declarative knowledge
that says what you're looking for.
And that's a process.
Well, what's a process in general?
It's a kind of hard to say. You can
think of it as like a magical spirit
that sort of lives in the computer and
does something.
And...
The thing that directs a process is a
pattern of rules called a procedure.
So procedures are the spells if you like
that control these magical spirits
that are the processes.
And... well I guess you know
everyone needs a magical language
and sorcerers, right,
real sorcerers use ancient Arcadian,
or Sumerian, or Babylonian or whatever.
We're gonna control our spirits
in a magical language called LISP,
which is a language
designed for talking about...
for casting the spells that
are procedures to direct the processes.
Now, it's very easy to learn LISP.
In fact, in a few minutes I'm gonna
teach you essentially all of LISP.
I'll teach you
essentially all of the rules...
And you shouldn't find
that particularly surprising.
That's sort of like saying it's very easy
to learn the rules of chess
and indeed in a few minutes
you can tell somebody the rules of chess
but of course
that's very different from saying
you understand
the implications of those rules
and how to use those rules
to become a masterful chess player.
Well, LISP is the same way.
We're gonna state the rules in a few
minutes and it will be very easy to see,
but what's really hard is gonna be
the implications of those rules.
How you exploit those rules
to be a master programmer.
And the implications of those rules
are gonna take us the...
well, the whole rest of this subject
and of course way beyond.
OK. So, in computer science
we're in the business of formalizing the
sort of 'how to' imperative knowledge.
Right? How to do stuff.
And real issues
of computer science are of course not,
you know,
telling people how to do square roots.
'Cause if that was all it was
it wouldn't be no big deal.
The real problems come when
we try to build very-very large systems.
Right? Computer programs
that are thousands of pages long.
So long that nobody can really
hold them in their heads all at once.
And the only reason that that's possible
is because there are techniques...
There are techniques...
for controlling the complexity...
of these large systems.
And these techniques for
controlling complexity
are what this course is really about.
And in some sense that's really
what computer science is about.
Now that may seem
like a very strange thing to say,
because after all a lot of people
beside computer scientists
deal with controlling complexity.
A large airliner
is an extremely complex system.
And the aeronautical engineers
who design that air,
you know,
are dealing with the men's complexity.
But there's a difference
between that kind of complexity and
what we deal with in computer science.
And that is that computer science
in some sense isn't real.
You see, when an engineer
is designing a physical system
that's made out of real parts, right,
the engineers who worry about that
have to address problems of tolerance and
approximation and noise in the system.
So, for example, as an electrical
engineer I can go off and easily build
a one-stage amplifier
or a two-stage amplifier.
And I can imagine cascading a lot of
them to build a million-stage amplifier,
But it's ridiculous to build
such a thing, because
long before the millionth stage the
thermal noise in those components
way at the beginning is gonna get amplified
and make the whole thing meaningless.
Computer science
deals with idealized components.
We know as much as we want
about these little programming data pieces
that we're fitting things together.
So there's... We don't have to worry
about tolerance and that means
that in building a large program
there is not all that much difference
between what I can build
and what I can imagine.
Because the parts of these abstract
entities that I know as much as I want.
I know about them
as precisely as I'd like.
So as opposed
to other kinds of engineering
where the constraints on what
you can build are the constraints
of physical systems, the constraints
of physics and noise and approximation.
The constraints imposed...
in building large software systems
are the limitations of our own minds.
So in that sense computer science
is like an abstract form of engineering.
It's the kind of engineering
where you ignore the constraints
that are imposed by reality.
OK. Well, what are...
some of these techniques?
They are not special to computer science.
First technique which is used in all of
engineering is kind of abstraction
called black-box abstraction.
Take something and build a box about it.
Let's see for example
if we looked at that square root method
I might want to take that and...
build a box that sort of says
'to find a square root of x'
Now it might be
a whole complicated set of rules
and that might end up being a kind of
thing where I can put in say 36 and say
what's the square root of 36
and out comes 6.
And the important thing is that I'd like
to design that
so that if George comes along and would
like to compute, say, the square root
of A plus the square root of B he can
take this thing and use it as a module
without having to look inside and build
something that looks like this
like an A and B, and a square root box,
and another square root box,
and then something that adds.
Now it would put out the answer.
And you can see, just from the fact that
I wanna do that is from George's point
of view the internals of what's in here
should not be important.
So, for instance, it shouldn't matter
that when I wrote this I said
I wanna find the square root of X.
I could have said the square root of Y.
Or the square root of A.
Or anything at all.
And that's the fundamental notion
of putting something in a box...
using black-box abstraction
to suppress detail.
And the reason for that is that you
wanna go of and build bigger boxes.
Now, there's another reason for doing
black-box abstraction.
Other than you wanna suppress detail
for building bigger boxes.
Sometimes you wanna say that your way of
doing something, your 'how to' method
is an instance of a more general thing.
And you'd like your language to be able
to express that generality.
Let me show you another example sticking
with square root. Let's go back
and take another look at that slide
with the square root algorithm on it.
Remember what that says? That says in
order to do something I'll make a guess,
and I'll improve that guess, and I
sort of keep improving that guess.
So, there's a general strategy
of looking for something.
And the way I find it
is that I keep improving it.
Now that's a particular case of another
kind of strategy
for finding a fixed point of something.
To have fixed point of a function...
A fixed point... of a function...
is something... is a value...
Fixed point of a function F is a value Y
such that F of Y equals Y.
And the way I might do that...
is start with a guess, and if I want
something that doesn't change
when I keep applying F
is I keep applying F over and over
until that result doesn't change very
much. So there is a general strategy
and then for example
to compute the square root of X
I can try and find a fixed point
of the function which takes
Y to the average of X over Y.
And the idea of that is that if I really
had Y equal to the square root of X
then Y and X over Y
would be the same value.
They'd both be the square root of X.
Right? Cause X over the square root of X
is the square root of X.
And so the average, if Y were equal to
the square root of X
then the average wouldn't change.
So the square root of X is a fixed point
of that particular function.
Now, what I'd like to have...
I'd like to express the general strategy
for finding fixed points. So what
I might imagine doing is to find...
is to be able to use my language
to define a box that says fixed point.
Just like I could make a box that says
square root and I'd like to be able
to express this in my language.
So I'd like to express not only the
imperative how to knowledge
about particular thing like square root,
but I'd like to be able to express
the imperative knowledge of how to do a
general thing like how to find fixed point.
And in fact let's go back
and look at that slide again.
See, not only is...
is this a piece of imperative
knowledge how to find a fixed point,
but over here at the bottom there's another
piece of imperative knowledge,
which says one way to compute square root
is to apply
this general fixed point method.
So I'd like to also be able to express
that imperative knowledge.
What would that look like? That would
say this fixed point box is such that
if I input to it the function that takes
Y to the average of Y and X over Y
than what should come out of that
fixed point box is...
a method for finding square roots.
So in these boxes we're building we're
not only building boxes that
you input numbers and output numbers.
We're gonna be building in boxes
that in effect compute methods
like finding square root.
And might take as their inputs functions
like Y goes
to the average of Y and X over Y.
Reason we wanna do that...
see, the reason...
This is a procedure or end up being
a procedure as we'll see,
whose value is another procedure. The
reason we wanna do that is because
procedures are gonna be our ways of
talking about imperative knowledge.
And the way to make that very powerful
is to be able to talk
about other kinds of knowledge.
So, here is a procedure that in fact
talks about another procedure.
And the general strategy that itself
talks about general strategies.
OK. Well, our first topic in this course
(there will be three major topics)
will be black-box abstraction. Let's look
at that in a little bit more detail.
Well, what we're gonna do is we will...
We'll start out talking about how LISP
is built up out of primitive objects,
what is the language supply with us.
And we'll see that they are
primitive procedures and primitive data.
Then we're gonna see
how do you take those primitives
and combine them
to make more complicated things.
Means of combination.
And what we'll see is that they're
ways of putting things together,
putting primitive procedures together
to make more complicated procedures.
And we'll see how to put primitive data
together to make compound data.
Then we'll say:
well, having made those compound things,
how do you abstract them?
How do you put
those black boxes around them
so you can use them as
components in more complex things?
And we'll see
that's done by defining procedures and
a technique for dealing with
compound data called data abstraction.
And then
what's maybe the most important thing is
going from just the rules
to how does an expert work.
How do you express common
patterns of doing things like saying
well, there's a
general method of fixed point
and square root
is a particular case of that.
And we're gonna use
I've already hinted that it's something
called higher order procedures, namely
procedures, whose inputs
and outputs are themselves procedures.
And we will also see
something very interesting we'll see
as we go further and further on
and become more abstract
there'll be very...
well... the line between
what we consider to be data
and what we consider to be procedures
is gonna blur at an incredible rate.
Right, well, that's our first subject,
black-box abstraction.
Let's look at the second topic.
I can introduce it...
Let's see that like this.
Suppose I want to express the idea.
Remember, we're talking about ideas.
Suppose, I wanna express the idea that
I can take something
and multiply it by
the sum of two other things.
So for example I might say
If I add 1 and 3
and multiply that by 2 I get 8.
But I'm talking about general idea
of what's called linear combination.
That you can add two things
and multiply them by something else.
It's very easy when I think
about it for numbers but suppose I...
I also want to use
that same idea to think about
I could add two vectors a1 and a2
and then scale them
by some factor x and get another vector.
Or I might say I wanna think
about a1 and a2 as being polynomials.
And I might wanna
add those two polynomials
and then multiply them by two
to get a more complicated one.
Or a1 and a2 might be electrical signals
and I might wanna think about
summing those two electrical signals
and then putting the whole thing
to an amplifier and multiplying it by
some factor of two or something.
The idea is I wanna think
about the general notion of that.
Now, if our language
is gonna be a good language for
expressing those kinds of general ideas.
It's if I really can do that.
So I'd like to be able to say
I gonna multiply by x the sum of a1 and a2
and I'd like that
to express the general idea
of all different kinds of things
that a1 and a2 could be.
Now, if you think about that, there's
a problem because after all the actual
primitive operations that go on in the
machine are obviously gonna be different
if I'm adding two numbers
then if I'm adding two polynomials.
Or if I'm adding the representation
of two electrical signals or waveforms.
Somewhere there has to be the knowledge
of the kinds of various things that
you can add and the ways of adding them.
Now, to construct such a system,
the question is
where do I put that knowledge?
How do I think about the different
kinds of choices I have? And if tomorrow
George comes up with a new kind of object
that might be added and multiplied,
how do I add George's new object to this
system without screwing up everything
that was already there?
That's gonna be the second big topic,
the way of controlling that kind
of complexity. And the way you do that
is by establishing
conventional interfaces.
Agreed upon ways
of plugging things together,
just like in electrical engineering
people have standard
impedances for connectors.
And then you know if you build something
with one of the standard impedances, you
can plug it together with something else.
That's gonna be our second
large topic, conventional interfaces.
What we're gonna see
is first we're gonna talk about
the problem of generic operations,
which is the one I alluded to.
Things like plus that have to
work with all different kinds of data.
So we'll talk about generic operations.
Then we're gonna talk
about really large scale structures.
How do you put together
very large programs that model
the kinds of complex systems in the
real world that you'd like to model.
And what we're gonna see is that
there are two very important metaphors
for putting together such systems.
One is called object oriented
programming where you sort of think of
your system as a kind of society
for little things that interact
by sending information between them.
And then a second one is
operations on aggregates called streams
where you think of a large system
put together kind of
like a signal processing engineer
puts together a large electrical system.
That's gonna be our second topic.
Now, the third thing we're gonna come to
the third basic technique for controlling
complexity is making new languages.
Cause sometimes,
when you sort of overwhelmed
by the complexity of your design,
the way that you control that complexity
is to pick a new design language.
And the purpose of the new design language
will be to highlight
different aspects of the system.
It'll suppress some kinds of details
and emphasize other kinds of details.
This is gonna be the third,
the most magical part of the course.
We're gonna start out
by actually looking at the technology
for building new computer languages
and the first thing we're
gonna do is actually build in LISP...
We're gonna express in LISP
the process of interpreting LISP itself.
And that's gonna be
very sort of self-circular thing.
There's a little mystical symbol
that has to do with that.
We'll see that the process
of interpreting LISP is sort of...
a giant wheel
of two processes, apply and eval,
which sort of constantly
reduce expressions to each other.
Now, we're gonna see also other magical
things. Here's another magical symbol.
This is kind of the...
This is sort of the Y-operator,
which is in some sense the expression of
infinity inside our procedural language.
We'll take a look at that.
In any case this section of the course
is called metalinguistic abstraction.
By talking, abstracting by talking about
how you construct new languages
as I said we're gonna start out
by looking at the process of
interpretation. We're gonna look at
this apply/eval loop.
and build LISP.
Then just to show you
that this is very general
we're gonna use exactly the same technology
to build a very different kind of language,
a so-called logic programming language,
where you don't really talk
about procedures at all
that have inputs and outputs.
What you do is talk about
relations between things.
And then finally
we're gonna talk about how you
implement these things very concretely
on a very simplest kind of machines.
Even... we'll see something like this,
which is... this is a picture of a chip
which is the LISP interpreter
that we will be talking about,
then in hardware.
OK. Well, there's an outline
of the course, three big topics:
Black-box abstraction, conventional
interfaces, metalinguistic abstraction.
Well, let's take a break now
and then we'll get started.
Well, let's actually
start in learning LISP now.
Actually, we'll start up by learning
something much more important.
Maybe, the very most
important thing in this course.
Which is not LISP in particular,
of course, but rather a general framework
for thinking about languages.
I already alluded to when somebody tells
you they gonna show you a language,
what you should say is:
alright, what I'd like you to tell me
is what are the primitive elements?
What does the language come with?
Then, what are the ways
you put those together?
What are the means of combination?
What are the things that allow you
to take these primitive elements
and build bigger things out of them?
What are the ways
of putting things together?
And then,
what are the means of abstraction?
How do we take those complicated things
and draw those boxes around them?
How do we name them
so that we can now use them
as if they were primitive elements
in making still more complex things
and so on, and so on, and so on?
So, when someone says to you:
Gee, I have a great new computer language!
You don't say: How many characters
does it take to invert a matrix?
Right? It's irrelevant.
Right? What you say is:
How, if the language
did not come with matrices built in
or with something else built in,
how could I then build that thing?
What are the means of combination
which would allow me to do that?
And then,
what are the means of the abstraction,
which allow me
then to use those as elements
in making more complicated things yet.
Well, we're gonna see
that LISP has some primitive data
and some primitive procedures.
In fact let's really start.
And here's a piece of
primitive data in LISP. Let's see...
Number 3.
Actually, from being very pedantic
that's not the number 3.
That's some symbol that represents...
plays those concepts of the number 3.
And here's another...
here's some more primitive data in LISP.
Seventeen point four.
Actually, some representation of 17.4.
And, here's another one. Five.
Here's another
primitive object that's built in LISP.
Addition. Actually, if we used the same
kind of pedantic, this is a name
for the primitive method
that's adding things.
Just like this is a name
for what played those number 3,
this is a name for what played
those concept of how you add things.
So those are some primitive elements.
I can put them together.
I can say, gee,
what's the sum of 3 and 17.4 and 5?
The way I do that is to say let's apply
the sum operator to these three numbers.
And I should get what? 8, 17,.. 25.4.
So, I should be able to ask LISP
what the value of this is.
And it'll return 25.4.
Let's introduce some names.
This thing that I typed
is called the combination.
And a combination consists in general
of applying an operator
(so, this is an operator)
to some operands
(these are the operands).
And of course
I can make more complex things.
The reason I can get complexity out of
this is because the operands themselves
in general can be combinations.
So, for instance, I could say what is
the sum of 3 and the product of 5 and 6,
and 8, and 2.
And I should get, let's see...
30, 40,.. 43.
So LISP should tell me that that's 43.
Forming combinations...
well, is the basic means of combination
that we'll be looking in.
And then, well, you see some syntax here.
LISP uses what is called prefix notation
which means that the operator...
is written to the left of the operands.
It's just a convention.
And note that it's fully parenthesized.
And the parentheses
make it completely unambiguous.
So by looking at this I can see that
there's the operator and there are
one,.. two,.. three,.. four operands.
And I can see that the second operand
here is itself some combination,
that has one operator and two operands.
Parentheses in LISP are a little bit...
well, are very unlike
parentheses in conventional mathematics.
In mathematics we sort of
use them to mean grouping.
And it sort of doesn't hurt if sometimes
you leave out parentheses if
people understand that that's a group.
And in general it doesn't hurt
if put in extra parentheses
because that maybe makes the grouping
more distinct. LISP is not like that!
In LISP you can't leave out parentheses.
And you can't put in extra parentheses.
'Cause putting in parentheses
always means exactly and precisely
this is a combination,
which has meaning
applying operator to operands.
And if I left this out,..
if I left those parentheses out
it would mean something else.
In fact, the way to think about this
is really what I'm doing
when I write something like this
is writing a tree.
So, this combination is a tree
that has a plus, and then a 3,
and then something else,
and then 8, and a 2.
And then this something else here
is itself a little subtree
that has a star, and a 5, and a 6.
And the way to think of that
is really what's going on
are rewriting these trees,
and parentheses are just a way
to write this two-dimensional structure
as a linear character string.
Because when LISP first started
then people had teletypes
or punchcards or whatever...
This was more convenient.
Maybe if LISP started today
the syntax of LISP would look like that.
Well, let's look at what that
actually looks like on the computer.
Here I have a LISP
interaction set up. There's an editor.
And on top I'm gonna type some values
and ask LISP what they are.
So, for instance I can say to LISP
what's the value of that symbol?
That's 3. And I ask LISP to evaluate it.
And now you see LISP has returned
on the bottom
and said oh, yeah, that's 3.
Or I can say what's the sum of 3 and 4
and 8? What's that combination?
And I ask LISP to evaluate it.
That's 15.
Or I can type in something more
complicated. I can say what's the sum...
of the product of 3...
and the sum of 7 and 19.5...
And you notice here
that LISP has something built in
that helps me keep track
of all these parentheses. Watch
as I type the next close parenthesis
which is gonna close
the combination starting with the star.
The opening one will flash.
There. I'll rub those out and do it again...
Type close
and you see that closes the plus.
Close again that closes the star.
Now I'm back to the sum
and maybe I'm gonna add that all to 4
That closes the plus,
now I have a complete combination.
And I can ask LISP for the value
of that. That kind of paren balancing
is something that's built into a lot
of LISP systems to help you keep track
because it is kind of boring
just by hand doing all this parentheses.
There's another kind of convention
for keeping track of parentheses.
Let me write another
complicated combination.
Let's say the sum of
the product of 3 and 5,
and add that to something and now
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna indent so
that the operands are written vertically
Let's the sum of that and the product
of 47 and... let's say the product of 47
with the difference of 20 and 6.8
(that means subtract 6.8 from 20).
Now you see the parentheses close
close the minus, close the star...
And now let's get another operator...
You see,
the LISP editor here is indenting
to the right position automatically
to help me keep track.
Again, I'll close that list parentheses
again, you see, it balances the plus
Right, now I can say
what's the value of that?
Right, so, those two things:
indenting to the right level,
which is called pretty printing,
and flashing parentheses
are two things that a lot of
LISP systems have built in
to help you keep track
and you should learn how to use them.
OK. Well, those are the primitives.
There's a means of combination.
Now let's go to the means of abstraction.
I'd like to be able to take the idea
that I do some combination like this
and abstract it and give it a simple
name so I can use that as an element,
and I do that in LISP with define.
So I could say for example define A
to be the product of 5 and 5.
And now I could say for example to LISP
what is the product of A and A?
And this should be 25,
and this should be 625.
And then crucial thing I can now use A.
Here I've used it in the combination,
but I could use that in other more
complicated things that I name in turn.
So I could say define B
to be the sum of A and product of 5 and A.
... and close the plus...
Let's take a look at that on the
computer and see how that looks.
So, well, I'll just type
what wrote on the board.
I could say define A
to be the product of 5 and 5.
I'll tell that to LISP
and notice what LISP responded
there with with an A in the bottom.
In general
when you type in a definition of LISP
it responds with the symbol being defined.
Now, I could say to LISP
what is the product of A and A?
So it says 625.
I can define B
to be the sum of A and the product
of 5 and A, close the paren,
close the star, close the plus.
Close the define.
LISP says:
OK. B.
There on the bottom. And now
I can say to LISP what's the value of B?
And I can say something more
complicated, like what's the sum
of A and the quotient of B and 5?
That slash is divide,
another primitive operator.
I've divided B by 5 and added it to A.
LISP says:
OK. That's 55.
Alright. So, there's what it looks like.
There's the basic means
of defining something.
It's the simplest kind of naming,
but it's not really very powerful.
See, what I'd really like to name...
I'm gonna talk about general methods...
I'd like to name all the general idea
that for example I could multiply 5 by 5
... or 6 by 6,..
...  or 1001 by 1001,
... or 1001.7 by 1001.7
Or I'd like to be able
to name the general idea
of multiplying something by itself.
We know that it is
that's called squaring.
And the way I can do that in LISP
is I can say
define...
to square some thing X
multiply X by itself.
And then, having done that, I could say
to LISP for example what's
the square of 10? And LISP will say 100.
Let's actually look at that
a little more closely.
There's the definition of square.
To square something
multiply it by itself.
You see this X here.
Right? That X is kind of a pronoun which
is the something that I'm gonna square.
And what I do is I multiply X by itself.
OK. So, there's a notation
for defining a procedure.
Actually this is a little bit confusing,
because this is sort of how I
might use square and I say square of X,
or square of 10,
but it's not making it very clear
that I'm actually naming something.
So, let me write this
definition in another way
that makes a little bit more clear
that I'm naming something.
I'll say define square
to be...
lambda of X times X X.
Here I'm naming something square.
Just like over here
I'm naming something A.
The thing that I'm naming square...
Here I named... the thing that I named A
was the value of this combination.
Here the thing that I'm naming square
is this thing that begins with lambda
and lambda is LISP's way
of saying 'make a procedure'.
Let's look at that
more closely on a slide.
The way I read that definition is to say
I define square to be make a procedure
(that's what the lambda is)
Make a procedure
with an argument named X
and what it does is return
the result of multiplying X by itself.
Now, in general we're gonna be using...
We're gonna be using
this top form of defining.
This is 'cause
it's a little bit more convenient.
But don't lose sight
of the fact that it's really this.
In fact as far as
the LISP interpreter is concerned
there's no difference between
typing this to it and typing this to it.
And there's a word for that:
Syntactic sugar.
What syntactic sugar means it's having
somewhat more convenient
surface forms for typing something.
So, this is just really syntactic sugar
for this underlying thing with the lambda.
And the reason you should
remember that is don't forget
that when I write something like this
I'm really naming something.
I'm naming something square
and this something that
I'm naming square is a procedure
that's getting constructed.
OK. Well, let's look at that
on the computer too.
So, I'll come in and I'll say define
square of X to be times X X.
And I can...
OK. I'll tell LISP that.
It says square as I have named
something square and having done that,
I can ask LISP
for what's the square of 1001.
Or in general I could say
what's the square of the sum of 5 and 7?
Right? Square of 12 is 144.
Or I can use square itself
as an element in some combination.
I can say what's the sum of
the square of 3 and the square of 4?
Right? 9 and 16 is 25.
Or I can use square as an element
in some much more complicated thing.
I can say what's the square of
the square of the square of 1001?
And here's the square
of the square of the square of 1001.
Well, I can say to LISP what is square
itself? What's the value of that?
And LISP returns some conventional way
of telling me that that's a procedure
that's compound procedure square.
And the value of square is
this procedure. And the things
with the stars and the brackets
are just LISP's
conventional way of describing that.
OK. Let's look at...
at two more examples of defining.
Here are two more procedures.
I can define the average of X and Y
to be the sum of X and Y divided by 2.
Or, having had average and square,
I can use that to talk about
the mean square of something.
Which is the average
of the square of X and the square of Y.
So, for example having done that,
I could say what's the mean square
of 2 and 3? And I should get
the average of 4 and 9, which is 6.5.
The key thing here
is that having defined square
I can use it as if it were primitive.
So, if we look here on the slide...
If I look at mean-square...
The person defining mean-square
doesn't have to know at this point
whether square was
something built into the language
or whether it was a procedure
that was defined.
And that's key thing in LISP.
That you do not
make arbitrary distinctions
between things that happen
to be primitive in the language
and things that happen to be built in.
Person using it shouldn't even have
to know. So the things you construct
get used with all the power and
flexibility as if they were primitives.
In fact you can drive that home by
looking on the computer one more time.
We talked about plus. And in fact
if I come here on the computer screen
and say what is the value of plus?
Notice what LISP types out.
On the bottom there
it typed out compound procedure +.
Because in this system it turns out
that the addition operator
is itself a compound procedure.
And if I didn't just typed that in
you'd never know that
and it wouldn't make any
difference anyway. We don't care.
It's below the level of the
abstraction that we're dealing with.
So, the key thing is you can not tell,..
should not be able to tell
in general the difference
between things that are built in
and things that are compound.
Why is that?
Because the things that are compound
have an abstraction wrapper
wrapped around them.
OK. We've seen almost
all the elements of LISP now.
There's only one more we have to look at.
And that is how to make a case analysis.
Let me show you what I mean.
We might wanna think about the
mathematical definition
of the absolute value function.
I might say the absolute value of X
is the function which has the property
that it's negative of X
for X less than zero,
it's zero for X equal to zero,
and it's X for X greater than zero.
And LISP has a way of making case analysis.
Let me define for you absolute value.
Say define the absolute value of X is
conditional... This means
case analysis - cond.
If X is less than zero
the answer is negate X.
Right, what I've written here
is a clause. This is a...
This something is a conditional clause.
And it has two parts.
This part here is a predicate,..
condition, that's a condition.
The condition is expressed
by something called a predicate.
And a predicate in LISP
is some sort of thing
that returns either true or false.
And you see LISP has
a primitive procedure less than,
that tests
whether something is true or false.
And the other part of a clause
is an action or a thing to do
in the case where that's true.
And here what I'm doing is negating X.
The negation operator, well, the minus
sign in LISP is a little bit funny.
If there are two or more arguments...
if there are two arguments then it
subtracts the second one from the first.
We saw that. And if there's
one argument then it negates it.
So, this corresponds to that.
And there's another kind of clause. It
says in the case where X is equal to 0
the answer is zero.
And in the case where X is
greater than zero the answer is X.
Close that clause, close the cond,
close the definition.
There's a definition of absolute value
and you see that it's a case analysis
that looks very much like the
case analysis you use in mathematics.
OK. There's a somewhat different way
of writing a restricted case analysis.
Often you have a case analysis
where you only have one case.
Or you test something and
depending on whether
it's true or false you do something.
Here's another definition of absolute
value which looks almost the same,
which says if X is less then zero,
the result is negate X,
otherwise the answer is X.
We'll be using IF a lot. But again
the thing to remember is that this form
of absolute value
that you're looking at here
and then this one over here
that I wrote on the board
are essentially the same.
And IF and COND are
whichever way you like it.
You can think of COND
as syntactic sugar for IF,
or you can think of IF
as syntactic sugar for COND,
and it doesn't make any difference.
Person implementing
a LISP system will pick one
and implement the other in terms of that,
and it doesn't matter which one he pick.
OK. Why don't we break now
and then take some questions.
How come...
sometimes when I write define
I put an open paren here
and say define open paren
some thing or other,
and sometimes when I write this
I don't put an open paren?
OK. The answer is...
this particular form of define
where you say define some expression
is this very special thing
for defining procedures.
But again what it really means is I'm
defining this symbol square to be that.
So, the way you should think about it is
what define does is you write define
and then second thing you write
is this symbol here, no open paren,
this symbol you're defining.
And what you're defining it to be...
that's like here... and like here...
That's the sort of the
basic way you use define
and then there's
the special syntactic trick,
which allows you to define
procedures that look like this.
So, the difference is it's whether
or not you're defining a procedure.
Well, believe it or not,
you actually now know enough LISP
to write essentially
any numerical procedure,
that you'd write in a language
like Fortran or Basic or whatever,
well, essentially any other language.
You probably think
that's not believable, right?
Because you know that these languages
have things like for statements
and do...until/while or something.
But we don't really need any of that.
We're not gonna use
any of that in this course.
Let me show you
by again looking back at square root.
Let's go back to this
square root algorithm
of Heron of Alexandria.
Remember what that said?
It said to find an approximation to
the square root of X you make a guess,
you improve that guess by averaging
the guess and X over the guess,
you keep improving that
until the guess is good enough.
And I already alluded to the idea.
The idea is that
if the initial guess that she took...
if that initial guess was actually
equal to the square root of X,
then G here would be equal to X over G.
So if you hit the square root
averaging wouldn't change it.
IF the G that you pick was larger
than the square root of X
then X/G would be smaller
then the square root of X,
so that when you average G and X/G
you get something in between.
Right? So, if you pick a G that's too
small, your answer will be too large.
If you pick a G that's too large...
if the G is larger than the square
root of X then X/G will be smaller
than the square root of X.
So, averaging always
gives you something in between
and then it's not quite trivial
but it's possible to show that in fact
if G misses
the square root of X by a little bit
the average of G and X/G
will actually keep getting closer
to the square root of X.
So if you keep doing this enough
you'll eventually get as close
as you want and there's another fact
that you can always start out this
process by using 1 as an initial guess,
and it will always converge
to the square root of X.
Right? So, that is method of successive
averaging due to Heron of Alexandria.
Let's write it in LISP.
Well, the central idea is
what does it mean to try a guess
for the square root of X?
Let's write that. So we'll say
define...
to try a guess
for the square root of X...
What do we do?
We'll say if the guess is good enough...
If the guess is good enough
to be a guess for the square root of X,
then as an answer we'll take the guess.
Otherwise we will try the improved guess.
We'll improve that guess
for the square root of X
and will try that
as a guess for the square root of X.
... close the try,
close the if, close the define.
So, that's how we try a guess.
And then the next part of the process
said in order to compute square roots
we'll say define
to compute the square root of X
we will try 1 as a guess
for the square root of X.
Well, we have to define
a couple more things.
Well, we have to say how is a guess good
enough and how do we improve a guess.
So let's look at that.
The algorithm to improve the guess
Right? To improve a guess
for the square root of X we average...
That was the algorithm...
We average the guess
with the quotient of dividing X by the
guess. That's how we improve the guess.
And to tell whether a guess is good
enough for we have to decide something.
This is supposed to be a guess
for the square root of X.
So, one possible thing you can do
is say when you
take that guess and square it
do you get something very close to X?
For example one way to say that
is to say I square the guess,
subtract X from that and see if
the absolute value of that whole thing
is less than some small number,
which depends on my purposes.
OK. So, there's a...
there's a complete procedure
for how to compute the square root of X.
Let's look at
the structure of that a little bit.
I have the whole thing. I have the
notion of how to compute a square root.
That's some kind of module.
Right? That's some kind of black-box.
It's defined in terms of...
It's defined in terms of how to try
a guess for the square root of X.
Try is defined in terms of, well,
telling whether something is good enough
and telling how to improve something.
So, good enough...
Try is defined in terms of good-enough?
and improve.
And (let's see what else I'm filling)...
If you go down this tree
good-enough? was defined
in terms of absolute value and square.
And improve was defined
in terms of something called averaging
and then some other primitive operators.
Square root is defined in terms of try.
Try is defined in terms of good-enough?
and improve, but also try itself.
So try is also defined
in terms of how to try itself.
Well, that may give you some problem.
Your high school geometry teacher
probably told you that it's naughty
trying define things in terms of
themselves, cause it doesn't make sense.
But that's false.
Sometimes it makes perfect sense
to define things in terms of themselves.
And this is a case.
And we can look at that,
we can write down what this means
Let's say suppose I ask LISP
what the square root of 2 is.
Well, what does
the square root of 2 mean?
Well, that means I try 1
as a guess for the square root of 2.
Now, I look, I say gees, is 1 a good
enough guess for the square root of 2?
That depends on the test
that good-enough does.
And in this case
the good-enough will say no,
1 is not a good enough guess
for the square root of 2.
So, that will reduce to saying
I have to try
the improved and improved... improve 1
as a guess for the square root of 2
and try that as a guess
for the square root of 2.
Improving 1 as a guess for the square
root of 2 means I average 1 and 2/1.
So, this is gonna be the average...
this piece here will be the average
of 1 and the quotient of 2 by 1.
So, this piece here.
And I'm gonna try... And this is 1.5...
So, this square root of 2 reduces
to trying 1 for the square root of 2,
which reduces to trying 1.5
as a guess for the square root of 2.
Right? So that makes sense.
Let's look at the rest of the process.
Here, if I try 1.5, that reduces...
1.5 turns out to be not good enough
as a guess for the square root of 2.
So, that reduces to trying
the average of 1.5 and 2/1.5
as a guess for the square root of 2.
That average turns out to be 1.3333,
So, this whole thing reduces
to trying 1.3333 as a guess
for the square root of 2,and then so on.
Right? That reduces
to another call to good-enough.
1.4xxx and then it keeps going until the
process finally stops with something that
that good-enough thinks is good enough
which in this case is 1.4142xxx.
So, the process makes perfect sense.
This by the way
is called a recursive definition
And the ability to make
recursive definitions
is a source of incredible power.
I've hinted that it's the thing
that effectively allows you to do
these infinite computations that go on
until something is true.
Without having any other constructs other
than the ability to call a procedure.
Let's see there's one more thing
in this. Let me show you a variant
of this definition of square root.
Look here on this slide. Here is a...
Here's a sort of the same thing.
What I've done here is packaged
the definitions of improve and
good-enough and try inside square root.
So in fact what I've done
is I've built the square root box.
I've built a box that's this square root
procedure that someone can use.
They might put in 36 and get out 6.
And then packaged inside this box,
right, the definitions of try,
and good-enough, and improve.
So they're hidden inside this box
and the reason for doing that is that
if someone is using this square root...
if George is using this square root,
George probably doesn't care very much
that when I implemented square root
I had things inside there
called try and good-enough and improve.
And in fact, Harry
might have a cube root procedure
that has try and good-enough and improve
And in order to not get the whole system
confused it will be good for Harry
to package his internal procedures
inside his cube root procedure.
This is called block structure.
This particular way of packaging
internals inside of a definition.
And let's go back and look at this
slide again. The way to read this
this kind of procedure is
to say to define square root...
well, inside that definition
I'll have the definition of improve,
and the definition of good-enough,
and the definition of try.
And then subject to those definitions
the way I do square root is to try 1.
And notice here I don't have to say
1 as a guess for the square root of X.
Because since it's all inside this
square root it sort of has this X now.
OK. Well, let me summarize.
We started out with the idea
that what we're gonna be doing
is expressing imperative knowledge.
And in fact here's a slide that
summarizes the way we've looked at LISP.
We started out
by looking at some primitive elements:
addition, multiplication,
some predicates for testing whether
something is less than or something is equal
and in fact we saw really snickly
in the system we're actually using
these aren't actually primitives
but it doesn't matter.
What matters is we're gonna
use them as if they are primitives,
we're not gonna look inside.
We also have
some primitive data... some numbers.
We saw some means of composition, means
of combination, the basic one being
composing functions and building
combinations with operators and operands.
And there is some other things
like COND and IF and DEFINE.
But the main thing
about define in particular
was that it was the means of abstraction,
it was the way that we name things.
You can also see from this slide
not only where we've been
but holes we have to fill in.
At some point
we'll have to talk about how you combine
primitive data to get compound data,
and how you abstract data,
so you can use large clumps
of data as if they were primitive.
So, that's where we're going.
But before we do that for the next couple
of lectures we're gonna be talking about
first of all how it is that you make a
link between these procedures we write
and the processes
that happen in the machine.
And then how it is
that you start using the power of LISP
to talk not only about
these individual little computations
but about general
conventional methods of doing things.
OK. Are there any questions?
-Yes.If we'd defined A using parentheses
instead of as we did
what would be the difference?
-If I wrote this...
If I wrote that what I would be doing
is defining a procedure named A,
in this case a procedure of no arguments,
which when I ran it
would give me back 5 times 5.
- I mean you come over the same thing
except for you really got a difference.
- Right. And the difference...
the difference would be in the old one,
let me be a little bit clearer here...
Let's call this A like here.
And then pretend here just for contrast
I wrote define...
D to be the product of 5 and 5.
And the difference between those.
Let's think about interactions
with the LISP interpreter.
I would type in A
and LISP would return 25.
I could type in D...
if I just type in D, LISP would return
compound procedure D.
'Cause that's what it is,
it's a procedure.
I could run D. I could say
what's the value of running D?
Here is a combination with no operands.
And I see there are no operands.
I didn't put any after D.
And it would say Oh, that's 25.
Or I could say... just for completeness
if I typed in what's
the value of running A I get an error.
The error would be
the same one as over there.
The error would say sorry, 25,
which is the value of A, is not an
operator that I can apply to something.
OK.
Subtitles created by Sergey Khenkin
http://www.sicptitles.org