Eu gostaria de dar boas vindas
a este curso de Ciência da Computação.
Na realidade, esse é um jeito terrível de começar.
Ciência da Computação
é um nome terrível para este negócio.
Para começar isso não é Ciência.
Isso pode ser talvez engenharia...
ou talvez arte...
Ou nós atualmente vemos a computação...
geralmente chamada de 'ciência'...
na verdade tem muito mais em comum com a mágica.
Nós veremos isso neste curso.
Portanto isso não é ciência. E isso
também não é muito sobre computadores.
E isso não é sobre computadores
da mesma maneira que...
a Física não é realmente
sobre aceleradores de partículas...
e Biologia não é realmente
sobre microscópios e placas de Petri.
e não é sobre computadores
da mesma forma que a geometria
não é realmente sobre
usar instrumentos de medida.
Na verdade existe muita ligação
entre a ciência da computação e a geometria.
Para começar a Geometria
é outro campo com um nome ruim.
O nome vem de 'Gaia' que significa
terra e 'Metro' que significa medida.
Geometria originalmente significa
medir a terra... ou agrimensura.
E a razão para isso foi que
há milhares de anos
os sacerdotes egípcios
desenvolveram rudimentos da geometria
com o objetivo de descobrir como restaurar
os limites dos campos que eram destruídos
nas enchentes anuais do Nilo.
E para os egípcios que fizeram isso
a geometria era realmente
o uso de instrumentos de medida.
Agora, a razão pela qual nós pensamos que
a ciência da computação é sobre computadores
é bem parecida com a mesma razão
pela qual os egípcios pensaram que a geometria
era sobre instrumentos de medida.
E isso acontece quando
algumas áreas estão ainda começando e
você não as entende realmente bem
é muito fácil de confundir
a essência do que você está fazendo
com as ferramentas que você usa.
E realmente em algumas escalas
nós provavelmente conhecemos menos
sobre a essência da ciência da computação
do que os antigos egípcios
realmente conheciam sobre geometria.
Bem, o que eu quero dizer
sobre a essência da ciência da computação,
o que eu quero dizer sobre
a essência da geometria...
Vejam, é realmente verdade que os
egípcios frequentemente usavam instrumentos de medida.
Mas quando nós olhamos para eles agora
depois de alguns milhares de anos nós dizemos
"Caraca! O quê eles estavam fazendo?"
A importante tarefa que eles estavam fazendo
era começar a formalizar
noções sobre espaço e tempo.
Para começar um jeito de falarmos sobre...
a verdade matemática formal que nos leva
para o método axiomático, que nos leva para...
todo o tipo de matemática moderna.
Encontrar uma forma para expressarmos precisamente
o tão falado conhecimento 'declarativo'...
'o que é verdade'.
Bem, de maneira similar, eu acho que no futuro
as pessoas irão olhar para trás e dizer,
sim, aqueles
primitivos do século vinte
ficavam brincando
com coisas chamadas computadores,
mas na realidade o que eles estavam fazendo
era começando a aprender como formalizar...
formalizar intuições sobre... processos...
como fazer as coisas.
Começando a desenvolver uma maneira...
para falar precisamente
sobre o conhecimento do 'como fazer',
ao contrário da geometria
que fala sobre o 'o que é verdade'.
Deixe-me dar um exemplo disso.
Vamos dar uma olhada... Aqui está
um pouco de... um pouco de matemática.
Certo? Isso diz o que uma raiz quadrada é.
A raiz quadrada de X é o número Y
tal que o quadrado de Y é igual a X
e Y é maior que zero.
Isso é uma boa definição na matemática,
mas somente dizer o que é uma raiz quadrada
não diz absolutamente nada sobre...
sobre
como você pode sair por aí e encontrar uma raiz.
Vamos comparar isso
com um pouco de conhecimento imperativo.
Certo? Como você pode
sair por aí e achar uma raiz quadrada.
Esse fato também veio do Egito.
Não de um Egito muito antigo.
Este é um algoritmo
de Heron de Alexandria
que encontra a raiz quadrada
através de médias sucessivas.
E o que isso diz é...
Para se encontrar uma raiz quadrada...
... para encontrar uma raiz quadrada
você faz um palpite,
você melhora este palpite,
e o jeito que você melhora o palpite é
calculando a média do palpite e X sobre o palpite
(nós falaremos um pouco mais tarde
sobre o porquê disso ser possível)
e você continua a melhorar
o palpite enquanto ele for bom o suficiente.
Esse é um método.
É como fazer alguma coisa.
Ao contrário do conhecimento declarativo
que fala sobre o quê você está procurando.
E isso é um processo.
Bem, que processo na realidade?
Isso é algo difícil de dizer. Você pode
pensar nisso como sendo um espírito mágico
das coisas que vivem e fazem algo
em um computador.
E...
A coisa que direciona o processo é um
padrão de regras chamada procedimento.
Então, procedimentos são os feitiços que você usa
para controlar estes espíritos mágicos
que são os processos.
E... bem, eu imagino que vocês saibam que
qualquer um precisa de uma linguagem mágica
e de feiticeiros, veja,
feiticeiros verdadeiros usavam o Arcádio antigo,
ou Sumério, ou Babilônico ou outra coisa.
Nós vamos controlar nossos espíritos
com uma linguagem mágica chamada LISP,
que é uma linguagem
projetada para falar com...
para lançar feitiços que
são procedimentos que guiam os processos.
Agora, é muito fácil de aprender LISP.
De fato, em alguns minutos eu irei
ensinar para vocês praticamente tudo sobre LISP.
Eu irei ensinar para vocês
praticamente todas as regras...
E vocês não devem achar
isso surpreendente.
Isso é como dizer que é muito fácil
aprender as regras do xadrez
e realmente em alguns minutos
você poderá falar para qualquer um as regras do xadrez
mas claro que
isso é muito diferente de dizer
que você entendeu
as implicações dessas regras
e como usar essas regras
para se tornar um mestre no jogo.
Bem, com LISP é a mesma coisa.
Nós iremos definir as regras em alguns
minutos e isso será muito fácil de ver,
mas o que é realmente difícil
é a implicação dessas regras.
Como vocês poderão explorar essas regras
para se tornarem um grande programador.
E as implicações dessas regras
irão nos tomar...
bem, todo o resto do assunto
e muito mais.
OK. Então, em ciência da computação
nós estamos querendo formalizar
o conhecimento imperativo do 'como fazer'.
Certo? Como fazer as coisas.
E as reais questões
da ciência da computação não são obviamente,
vocês sabem,
dizer para as pessoas como encontrar raízes quadradas.
Porquê se fosse essa a questão
não seria grande coisa.
Os problemas reais aparecem quando
nós tentamos construir sistemas muito, muito grandes.
Certo? Programas de computador
que têm milhares de páginas.
Tão grandes que ninguém consegue realmente
guardá-los na cabeça de uma vez só.
E a única razão disso ser possível
é porque existem técnicas...
Existem técnicas...
para controlar a complexidade...
desses sistemas gigantescos.
E essas técnicas de
controle de complexidade
são o real objetivo desse curso.
E em certo sentido isso é realmente
sobre o quê a ciência da computação é.
Agora pode parecer
algo muito estranho de dizer,
porque existem várias pessoas
ao lado dos cientistas da computação
que lidam com o controle da complexidade.
Um controladador de vôo
é um sistema extremamente complexo.
E os engenheiros aeronáuticos
que projetam este sistemas,
vocês sabem,
eles estão lidando com a complexidade do homem.
Mas existe uma diferença
entre esse tipo de complexidade e
e aquela que lidamos na ciência da computação.
E isso significa que a ciência da computação
de algumas formas não é real.
Veja, quando um engenheiro
está projetando um sistema físico
ele é feito de partes reais, certo?
Os engenheiros que se preocupam com isso
devem tratar problemas de tolerância,
aproximações e ruídos no sistema.
Então, por exemplo, sendo um engenheiro
eletricista eu posso sair e facilmente construir
um amplificar de um estágio
ou de dois estágios.
E eu posso imaginar como arranjar um monte
deles para construir um amplificador de milhões de estágios.
Mas é ridículo construir
uma coisa dessas, porque
depois de milhões de estágios
o ruído térmico nestes componentes
será cada vez mais amplificado,
levando a uma solução sem sentido algum.
A ciência da computação
lida com componentes idealizados.
Nós sabemos o que queremos saber
sobre estes pequenos dados de programação
que estamos juntando.
Sendo assim... Nós não precisamos nos preocupar
com tolerância e isso significa
que ao contruir um programa grande
não existe tanta diferença assim
entre o que eu consigo construir
e o que eu consigo imaginar.
Porque as partes disso abstraem
entidades que eu conheço o quanto eu quero.
Eu sei sobre elas
somente o que eu gostaria de saber.
Então, ao contrário
de outros tipos de engenharia
onde as restrições sobre o quê
você pode construir são as restrições
dos sistemas físicos, as restrições
da física, ruído e aproximação.
As restrições impostas...
para se construir grandes sistemas de software
são as limitações da nossa própria mente.
Então, neste sentido a ciência da computação
é como uma forma abstrata da engenharia.
É um tipo de engenharia
onde você pode ignorar as limitações
que são impostas pela realidade.
OK. Bem, quais são...
algumas destas técnicas?
Elas não são específicas para a ciência da computação.
A primeira técnica que é usado em todo tipo de
engenharia é um tipo de abstração
chamada de abstração de caixa-preta.
Pegue alguma coisa e construa uma caixa para ela.
Vejamos por exemplo
se analisarmos o método de raiz quadrada
Eu poderia querer assumir isso e...
construir uma caixa que signifique
'encontrar a raiz quadrada de X'
Agora isso poderia ser
todo um conjunto complicado de regras
e poderia acabar sendo um tipo de
coisa onde eu poderia colocar, digamos, 36 e perguntar
qual a raiz quadrada de 36
e a saída seria 6.
E o importante nisso é que eu poderia
projetá-lo de forma que
quando George viesse e quisesse
calcular, digamos, a raiz quadrada
de A mais a raiz quadrada de B ele poderia
pegar isso e usá-lo como um módulo
sem ter que olhar para dentro e construir
algo que se pareça com isso
como um A e um B, e uma caixa para a raiz quadrada,
e outra caixa de raiz quadrada
e então algo que some-as.
Agora ele iria dar a resposta.
E vocês podem ver, que eu quero fazer isso
a partir do ponto de vista
de Geroge, onde os detalhes internos do que está aqui
não devem ser importantes.
Então, por exemplo, não importa se
quando eu escrevo isso eu diga
eu quero encontrar a raiz de X.
Eu poderia ter pedido a raiz quadrada de Y.
Ou a raiz quadrada de A.
Ou simplesmente a raiz quadrada de nada.
E essa é a noção fundamental
para se colocar algo na caixa...
usando a abstração de caixa-preta
para esconder detalhes.
E a razão para isso é que vocês
irão querer sair e construir caixas maiores.
Agora, existe uma outra razão para fazermos
abstrações de caixa-preta.
Além disso vocês irão querer suprimir detalhes
para construir caixas ainda maiores.
Algumas vezes você diz que o seu jeito de
fazer as coisas, o seu método de 'como fazer'
é uma instância de algo mais geral.
E você gostaria que sua linguagem fosse capaz
de expressar essa generalidade.
Deixem-me mostrar um outro exemplo
com raiz quadrada. Vamos voltar atrás
e dar uma olhada no slide
com o algoritmo da raiz quadrada.
Lembram o que ele dizia? Ele dizia que
para fazer algo eu precisaria fazer um palpite,
e eu iria melhorar esse palpite, e
de alguma forma continuaria a melhorá-lo.
Então, existe uma estratégia geral
quando procuramos por algo.
E o jeito para eu encontrar algo
é continuar melhorando-o.
Agora, esse é uma caso particular de um outro
tipo de estratégia
para encontrar um ponto fixo de algo.
Para termos o ponto fixo de uma função...
Um ponto fixo... de uma função...
é algo... é um valor...
Ponto fixo de uma função F é um valor Y
tal que F de Y é igual a Y.
E a maneira que eu poderia fazer isso...
é começar com um palpite, e se eu quero
algo que não se altera
quando eu continuo aplicando F
é continuar aplicando F denovo, e denovo
enquanto o resultando não se alterar
muito. Então existe uma estratégia geral
e então, por exemplo,
para calcular a raiz quadrada de X
eu posso tentar achar um ponto fixo
de uma função que toma
Y sendo a média de X sobre Y.
E a idéia disso é que se eu realmente
tenho Y sendo a raiz quadrada de X
então Y e X sobre Y
teriam o mesmo valor.
Ambos seriam raízes quadradas de X.
Certo? Porque X sobre a raiz quadrada de X
é a raiz quadrada de X.
E então a média, se Y for igual à
raiz quadrada de X
então a média não mudaria.
Então a raiz quadrada de X é um ponto fixo
de uma função em particular.
Agora, o que eu gostaria de ter...
Eu gostaria expressar uma estratégia geral
para encontrar pontos fixos. Então o que
eu poderia imaginar fazendo isso é encontrar...
é ser capaz de usar a minha linguagem
para definir uma caixa que signifique 'ponto fixo'.
Da mesma forma que eu poderia criar uma caixa que diga
'raiz quadrada' e eu gostaria de ser capaz
de expressá-la em minha linguagem.
Então eu gostaria de expressar não somente
o conhecimento imperativo de 'como fazer'
sobre uma coisa particular como a raiz quadrada,
mas eu gostaria de ser capaz de expressar
o conhecimento imperativo de 'como fazer' para fazer
algo geral como encontrar um ponto fixo.
Então vamos voltar
e olhar aquele slide novamente.
Vejam, isso não é somente...
não é somente um pedaço de conhecimento
imperativo sobre como encontrar um ponto fixo.
Logo aqui no rodapé, há outro pedaço
de conhecimento imperativo
que diz que uma forma de computar uma raiz quadrada
é aplicar
o método geral de ponto fixo.
Então eu gostaria de também ser capaz de expressar
esse conhecimento imperativo.
Com o que se pareceria isso? Digamos
que uma caixa de 'ponto fixo' é algo que
quando dada como entrada a função que toma
Y como a média de Y e X sobre Y
a saída de uma caixa de
'ponto fixo' é...
um método para encontrar raízes quadradas.
Portanto nessas caixas não estamos apenas
construindo caixas onde
você insere números e obtém números como saída.
Nós iremos construir caixas
que por sua vez computam métodos
como encontrar a raiz quadrada
E que podem aceitar funções como entradas
como fazer o Y ir
para a média entre Y e X sobre Y.
A razão pela qual queremos fazer isso...
Veja, a razão...
Isso é um procedimento ou acaba se tornando
um procedimento como iremos ver
cujo valor é outro procedimento. A
a razão pela qual queremos fazer isso é porque
procedimentos serão a nossa maneira de
falar sobre conhecimento imperativo.
E a maneira de tornar isso algo poderoso
é poder falar
asobre outros tipos de conhecimento.
Então, aqui está um procedimento que na verdade
fala sobre outro procedimento.
And the general strategy that itself
talks about general strategies.
OK. Bom, nosso primeiro tópico neste curso
(haverá três grandes tópicos)
será a abstração da caixa-preta. Vamos olhar
para isso com um pouco mais de detalhes.
Bom, o que nós iremos fazer é que nós iremos...
Nós vamos começar falando sobre como LISP
é construído sobre objetos primitivos,
o que é que a linguagem nos fornece.
E nós veremos que eles são
Procedimentos primitivos e dados primitivos.
Então nós iremos ver
Como você pega esses primitivos
e os combina
para fazer coisas mais complicadas.
Maneiras de combinar.
E o que nós iremos ver é que eles são
Maneiras de combinar as coisas,
juntando procedimentos primitivos
para fazer procedimentos mais complicados.
E nós iremos como colocar dados primitivos
juntos para fazer dados compostos.
Então nós iremos dizer:
bom, tendo feito essas coisas compostas,
como você as abstrai?
Como você coloca
essas caixas pretas ao redor delas
para que você as use como
componentes em coisas mais complexas?
E nós iremos ver
que isso é feito definindo procedimentos e
uma técnica para lidar com
dados compostos chamada abstração de dados.
E então
o que talvez seja a coisa mais importante é
ir de apenas essas regras
para como fazer um trabalho especialista.
Como você expressa padrões comuns
de fazer as coisas como dizer
bem, existe um
método geral do ponto fixo
e a raiz quadrada
é um caso particular disso.
E nós iremos usar
Eu já mencionei que existe algo assim com
procedimentos de alto nível, como
procedimentos, cujas entradadas
e saídas são elas próprias procedimentos.
E nós também iremos ver
algo muito interessante, nós iremos ver
conforme formos prosseguindo
e nos tornamos mais abstratos
existirão muitas...
bem... a linha entre o que
nós consideramos como sendo dados
e o que nós consideramos procedimentos
vai borrar num ritmo incrível.
Bom, certo, esse é o nosso primeiro assunto
abstração da caixa preta.
Vamos olhar para o segundo tópico.
Eu posso introduzi-lo...
Vamos ver, assim
Suponha que eu queira expressar a idéia
Lembrem-se, nós estamos falando sobre idéias
Suponha, eu quero expressar a idéia de que
Eu posso pegar alguma coisa
e multiplicar isto pela
pela soma de duas outras coisas.
Então por exemplo eu posso dizer
Se eu adicionar 1 e 3
e multiplicar isso por 2 eu obtenho 8.
Mas eu estou falando sobre a idéia geral
Do que é chamado combinação linear.
Que você pode adicionar duas coisas
e multiplicá-las por outra coisa.
É muito fácil quando eu penso
quando eu penso sobre isso com números mas suponha que eu...
Eu também queira usar
essa mesma idéia para pensar sobre
Eu poderia adicionar dois vetores a1 e a2I could add two vectors a1 and a2
e então escalá-los
por um fator X para obter outro vetor.
Ou eu posso dizer que eu quero pensar
sobre a1 e a2 como sendo polinômios.
E eu posso querer
adicionar esses dois polinômiosadd those two polynomials
e então multiplicá-los por dois
para obter um mais complicado.
Ou a1 e a2 podem ser sinais elétricos
E eu posso querer pensar sobre
somar esses dois sinais elétricos
e entãso colocar a coisa toda
em um amplificador e multiplicá-lo por
algum fator de dois ou alguma coisa.
A idéia é que eu quero pensar
sobre a noção geral disso.
Agora, se a nossa linguagem
será uma boa linguagem para
expressar esse tipo de idéia geral.
Se eu realmente poderei fazer isso.
Então eu gostaria de ser capaz de poder dizer
Eu vou multiplicar por X a soma de a1 e a2
e eu gostaria de
expressar a idéia geral
de todas as diferentes coisas
que a1 e a2 podem ser.
Agora, se você pensar sobre isso,existe
um problema porque todas as
operações primitivas que vão para a
máquina serão obviamente diferentes
se eu estiver adicionando dois números
do que se eu estiver adicionando dois polinômios
Ou se estou adicionando a representação
de dois sinais elétricos ou ondas.
Em algum lugar deve existir o conhecimento
dos tipos de coisas que
você pode adicionar e as maneiras de adicioná-las
Agora, para construir um sistema assim
a questão é
onde eu coloco esse conhecimento?
Como eu penso sobre os diferentes
tipos de escolhas que eu tenho? E se amanhã
George aparecer com um novo tipo de objeto
que pode ser adicionado e multiplicado,
como eu adiciono o novo objeto de George a esse
sistema sem bagunçar tudo
que já estava lá?
Este será o segundo grande tópico
A maneira de controlar esse tipo de
complexidade. E a maneira pela qual você faz isso
é estabelecendo
interfaces convencionais.
Maneiras acordadas
de juntar as coisas,
assim como em engenharia elétrica
as pessoas tem impedâncias
padrão para conectores.
E então você sabe que se você construir algo
com uma dessas impedâncias padrão, você
pode uni-la com alguma outra coisa.
Este será o nosso segundo
grande tópico, interfaces convecionais.
O que nós iremos ver
é que primeiro nós iremos falar
sobre o problema das operações genéricas,
que é aquela a qual eu fiz alusão.
Coisas como a adição que devem
funcionar com todos os diferentes tipos de dados
Então nós iremos falar sobre operações genéricas.
Então nós iremos falar
sobre estruturas de grandes escalas.
Como você junta
programas muito grandes que modelam
os tipos de sistemas complexos do
mundo real que você gostaria de modelar.
E o que nós iremos ver é que
existem duas metáforas muito importantes
sobre juntar sistemas assim
Uma se chama programação orientada a
objetos na qual você meio que pensa sobre
o seu sistema como um tipo de sociedade
para pequenas coisas que interagem
mandando informações entre si.
E a segunda é
operações em agregados chamados fluxos
quando você pensa em um grande sistema
combinado como um
engenheiro de processamento de sinais
combina um grande sistema elétrico.
Este será o nosso segundo tópico.
Agora, a terceira coisa que iremos ver
A terceira técnica básica para controlar
complexidade é fazer novas linguagens.
Porque às vezes,
Quando você está sobrecarregado
pela complexidade do seu design,
A maneira pela qual você controla essa complexidade
é escolhendo uma nova linguagem de design.
E o propósito de uma nova linguagem de design
Será iluminar
diferentes aspectos do sistema.
Ela irá suprimir alguns detalhes
e enfatizar outros tipos de detalhes
Este será a terceira,
mais mágica parte do nosso curso
Nós iremos começar
olhando para a tecnologia
Para construir novas linguagens de computador
E a primeira coisa que iremos
fazer é construir em LISP...
Nós iremos expressar em LISP
o processo de interpretar o próprio LISP.
E isto será algo bastante auto-circular.
Existe um pequeno símbolo mística
que tem a ver com isso
Nós iremos ver que o processo
de interpretar LISP é algo como...
uma grande roda
de dois processos, Apply (aplicar) e Eval (avaliar),
que meio que constantemente
reduzem expressões entre si.
Now, we're gonna see also other magical
things. Here's another magical symbol.
This is kind of the...
This is sort of the Y-operator,
which is in some sense the expression of
infinity inside our procedural language.
We'll take a look at that.
In any case this section of the course
is called metalinguistic abstraction.
By talking, abstracting by talking about
how you construct new languages
as I said we're gonna start out
by looking at the process of
interpretation. We're gonna look at
this apply/eval loop.
and build LISP.
Then just to show you
that this is very general
we're gonna use exactly the same technology
to build a very different kind of language,
a so-called logic programming language,
where you don't really talk
about procedures at all
that have inputs and outputs.
What you do is talk about
relations between things.
And then finally
we're gonna talk about how you
implement these things very concretely
on a very simplest kind of machines.
Even... we'll see something like this,
which is... this is a picture of a chip
which is the LISP interpreter
that we will be talking about,
then in hardware.
OK. Well, there's an outline
of the course, three big topics:
Black-box abstraction, conventional
interfaces, metalinguistic abstraction.
Well, let's take a break now
and then we'll get started.
Well, let's actually
start in learning LISP now.
Actually, we'll start up by learning
something much more important.
Maybe, the very most
important thing in this course.
Which is not LISP in particular,
of course, but rather a general framework
for thinking about languages.
I already alluded to when somebody tells
you they gonna show you a language,
what you should say is:
alright, what I'd like you to tell me
is what are the primitive elements?
What does the language come with?
Then, what are the ways
you put those together?
What are the means of combination?
What are the things that allow you
to take these primitive elements
and build bigger things out of them?
What are the ways
of putting things together?
And then,
what are the means of abstraction?
How do we take those complicated things
and draw those boxes around them?
How do we name them
so that we can now use them
as if they were primitive elements
in making still more complex things
and so on, and so on, and so on?
So, when someone says to you:
Gee, I have a great new computer language!
You don't say: How many characters
does it take to invert a matrix?
Right? It's irrelevant.
Right? What you say is:
How, if the language
did not come with matrices built in
or with something else built in,
how could I then build that thing?
What are the means of combination
which would allow me to do that?
And then,
what are the means of the abstraction,
which allow me
then to use those as elements
in making more complicated things yet.
Well, we're gonna see
that LISP has some primitive data
and some primitive procedures.
In fact let's really start.
And here's a piece of
primitive data in LISP. Let's see...
Number 3.
Actually, from being very pedantic
that's not the number 3.
That's some symbol that represents...
plays those concepts of the number 3.
And here's another...
here's some more primitive data in LISP.
Seventeen point four.
Actually, some representation of 17.4.
And, here's another one. Five.
Here's another
primitive object that's built in LISP.
Addition. Actually, if we used the same
kind of pedantic, this is a name
for the primitive method
that's adding things.
Just like this is a name
for what played those number 3,
this is a name for what played
those concept of how you add things.
So those are some primitive elements.
I can put them together.
I can say, gee,
what's the sum of 3 and 17.4 and 5?
The way I do that is to say let's apply
the sum operator to these three numbers.
And I should get what? 8, 17,.. 25.4.
So, I should be able to ask LISP
what the value of this is.
And it'll return 25.4.
Let's introduce some names.
This thing that I typed
is called the combination.
And a combination consists in general
of applying an operator
(so, this is an operator)
to some operands
(these are the operands).
And of course
I can make more complex things.
The reason I can get complexity out of
this is because the operands themselves
in general can be combinations.
So, for instance, I could say what is
the sum of 3 and the product of 5 and 6,
and 8, and 2.
And I should get, let's see...
30, 40,.. 43.
So LISP should tell me that that's 43.
Forming combinations...
well, is the basic means of combination
that we'll be looking in.
And then, well, you see some syntax here.
LISP uses what is called prefix notation
which means that the operator...
is written to the left of the operands.
It's just a convention.
And note that it's fully parenthesized.
And the parentheses
make it completely unambiguous.
So by looking at this I can see that
there's the operator and there are
one,.. two,.. three,.. four operands.
And I can see that the second operand
here is itself some combination,
that has one operator and two operands.
Parentheses in LISP are a little bit...
well, are very unlike
parentheses in conventional mathematics.
In mathematics we sort of
use them to mean grouping.
And it sort of doesn't hurt if sometimes
you leave out parentheses if
people understand that that's a group.
And in general it doesn't hurt
if put in extra parentheses
because that maybe makes the grouping
more distinct. LISP is not like that!
In LISP you can't leave out parentheses.
And you can't put in extra parentheses.
'Cause putting in parentheses
always means exactly and precisely
this is a combination,
which has meaning
applying operator to operands.
And if I left this out,..
if I left those parentheses out
it would mean something else.
In fact, the way to think about this
is really what I'm doing
when I write something like this
is writing a tree.
So, this combination is a tree
that has a plus, and then a 3,
and then something else,
and then 8, and a 2.
And then this something else here
is itself a little subtree
that has a star, and a 5, and a 6.
And the way to think of that
is really what's going on
are rewriting these trees,
and parentheses are just a way
to write this two-dimensional structure
as a linear character string.
Because when LISP first started
then people had teletypes
or punchcards or whatever...
This was more convenient.
Maybe if LISP started today
the syntax of LISP would look like that.
Well, let's look at what that
actually looks like on the computer.
Here I have a LISP
interaction set up. There's an editor.
And on top I'm gonna type some values
and ask LISP what they are.
So, for instance I can say to LISP
what's the value of that symbol?
That's 3. And I ask LISP to evaluate it.
And now you see LISP has returned
on the bottom
and said oh, yeah, that's 3.
Or I can say what's the sum of 3 and 4
and 8? What's that combination?
And I ask LISP to evaluate it.
That's 15.
Or I can type in something more
complicated. I can say what's the sum...
of the product of 3...
and the sum of 7 and 19.5...
And you notice here
that LISP has something built in
that helps me keep track
of all these parentheses. Watch
as I type the next close parenthesis
which is gonna close
the combination starting with the star.
The opening one will flash.
There. I'll rub those out and do it again...
Type close
and you see that closes the plus.
Close again that closes the star.
Now I'm back to the sum
and maybe I'm gonna add that all to 4
That closes the plus,
now I have a complete combination.
And I can ask LISP for the value
of that. That kind of paren balancing
is something that's built into a lot
of LISP systems to help you keep track
because it is kind of boring
just by hand doing all this parentheses.
There's another kind of convention
for keeping track of parentheses.
Let me write another
complicated combination.
Let's say the sum of
the product of 3 and 5,
and add that to something and now
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna indent so
that the operands are written vertically
Let's the sum of that and the product
of 47 and... let's say the product of 47
with the difference of 20 and 6.8
(that means subtract 6.8 from 20).
Now you see the parentheses close
close the minus, close the star...
And now let's get another operator...
You see,
the LISP editor here is indenting
to the right position automatically
to help me keep track.
Again, I'll close that list parentheses
again, you see, it balances the plus
Right, now I can say
what's the value of that?
Right, so, those two things:
indenting to the right level,
which is called pretty printing,
and flashing parentheses
are two things that a lot of
LISP systems have built in
to help you keep track
and you should learn how to use them.
OK. Well, those are the primitives.
There's a means of combination.
Now let's go to the means of abstraction.
I'd like to be able to take the idea
that I do some combination like this
and abstract it and give it a simple
name so I can use that as an element,
and I do that in LISP with define.
So I could say for example define A
to be the product of 5 and 5.
And now I could say for example to LISP
what is the product of A and A?
And this should be 25,
and this should be 625.
And then crucial thing I can now use A.
Here I've used it in the combination,
but I could use that in other more
complicated things that I name in turn.
So I could say define B
to be the sum of A and product of 5 and A.
... and close the plus...
Let's take a look at that on the
computer and see how that looks.
So, well, I'll just type
what wrote on the board.
I could say define A
to be the product of 5 and 5.
I'll tell that to LISP
and notice what LISP responded
there with with an A in the bottom.
In general
when you type in a definition of LISP
it responds with the symbol being defined.
Now, I could say to LISP
what is the product of A and A?
So it says 625.
I can define B
to be the sum of A and the product
of 5 and A, close the paren,
close the star, close the plus.
Close the define.
LISP says:
OK. B.
There on the bottom. And now
I can say to LISP what's the value of B?
And I can say something more
complicated, like what's the sum
of A and the quotient of B and 5?
That slash is divide,
another primitive operator.
I've divided B by 5 and added it to A.
LISP says:
OK. That's 55.
Alright. So, there's what it looks like.
There's the basic means
of defining something.
It's the simplest kind of naming,
but it's not really very powerful.
See, what I'd really like to name...
I'm gonna talk about general methods...
I'd like to name all the general idea
that for example I could multiply 5 by 5
... or 6 by 6,..
...  or 1001 by 1001,
... or 1001.7 by 1001.7
Or I'd like to be able
to name the general idea
of multiplying something by itself.
We know that it is
that's called squaring.
And the way I can do that in LISP
is I can say
define...
to square some thing X
multiply X by itself.
And then, having done that, I could say
to LISP for example what's
the square of 10? And LISP will say 100.
Let's actually look at that
a little more closely.
There's the definition of square.
To square something
multiply it by itself.
You see this X here.
Right? That X is kind of a pronoun which
is the something that I'm gonna square.
And what I do is I multiply X by itself.
OK. So, there's a notation
for defining a procedure.
Actually this is a little bit confusing,
because this is sort of how I
might use square and I say square of X,
or square of 10,
but it's not making it very clear
that I'm actually naming something.
So, let me write this
definition in another way
that makes a little bit more clear
that I'm naming something.
I'll say define square
to be...
lambda of X times X X.
Here I'm naming something square.
Just like over here
I'm naming something A.
The thing that I'm naming square...
Here I named... the thing that I named A
was the value of this combination.
Here the thing that I'm naming square
is this thing that begins with lambda
and lambda is LISP's way
of saying 'make a procedure'.
Let's look at that
more closely on a slide.
The way I read that definition is to say
I define square to be make a procedure
(that's what the lambda is)
Make a procedure
with an argument named X
and what it does is return
the result of multiplying X by itself.
Now, in general we're gonna be using...
We're gonna be using
this top form of defining.
This is 'cause
it's a little bit more convenient.
But don't lose sight
of the fact that it's really this.
In fact as far as
the LISP interpreter is concerned
there's no difference between
typing this to it and typing this to it.
And there's a word for that:
Syntactic sugar.
What syntactic sugar means it's having
somewhat more convenient
surface forms for typing something.
So, this is just really syntactic sugar
for this underlying thing with the lambda.
And the reason you should
remember that is don't forget
that when I write something like this
I'm really naming something.
I'm naming something square
and this something that
I'm naming square is a procedure
that's getting constructed.
OK. Well, let's look at that
on the computer too.
So, I'll come in and I'll say define
square of X to be times X X.
And I can...
OK. I'll tell LISP that.
It says square as I have named
something square and having done that,
I can ask LISP
for what's the square of 1001.
Or in general I could say
what's the square of the sum of 5 and 7?
Right? Square of 12 is 144.
Or I can use square itself
as an element in some combination.
I can say what's the sum of
the square of 3 and the square of 4?
Right? 9 and 16 is 25.
Or I can use square as an element
in some much more complicated thing.
I can say what's the square of
the square of the square of 1001?
And here's the square
of the square of the square of 1001.
Well, I can say to LISP what is square
itself? What's the value of that?
And LISP returns some conventional way
of telling me that that's a procedure
that's compound procedure square.
And the value of square is
this procedure. And the things
with the stars and the brackets
are just LISP's
conventional way of describing that.
OK. Let's look at...
at two more examples of defining.
Here are two more procedures.
I can define the average of X and Y
to be the sum of X and Y divided by 2.
Or, having had average and square,
I can use that to talk about
the mean square of something.
Which is the average
of the square of X and the square of Y.
So, for example having done that,
I could say what's the mean square
of 2 and 3? And I should get
the average of 4 and 9, which is 6.5.
The key thing here
is that having defined square
I can use it as if it were primitive.
So, if we look here on the slide...
If I look at mean-square...
The person defining mean-square
doesn't have to know at this point
whether square was
something built into the language
or whether it was a procedure
that was defined.
And that's key thing in LISP.
That you do not
make arbitrary distinctions
between things that happen
to be primitive in the language
and things that happen to be built in.
Person using it shouldn't even have
to know. So the things you construct
get used with all the power and
flexibility as if they were primitives.
In fact you can drive that home by
looking on the computer one more time.
We talked about plus. And in fact
if I come here on the computer screen
and say what is the value of plus?
Notice what LISP types out.
On the bottom there
it typed out compound procedure +.
Because in this system it turns out
that the addition operator
is itself a compound procedure.
And if I didn't just typed that in
you'd never know that
and it wouldn't make any
difference anyway. We don't care.
It's below the level of the
abstraction that we're dealing with.
So, the key thing is you can not tell,..
should not be able to tell
in general the difference
between things that are built in
and things that are compound.
Why is that?
Because the things that are compound
have an abstraction wrapper
wrapped around them.
OK. We've seen almost
all the elements of LISP now.
There's only one more we have to look at.
And that is how to make a case analysis.
Let me show you what I mean.
We might wanna think about the
mathematical definition
of the absolute value function.
I might say the absolute value of X
is the function which has the property
that it's negative of X
for X less than zero,
it's zero for X equal to zero,
and it's X for X greater than zero.
And LISP has a way of making case analysis.
Let me define for you absolute value.
Say define the absolute value of X is
conditional... This means
case analysis - cond.
If X is less than zero
the answer is negate X.
Right, what I've written here
is a clause. This is a...
This something is a conditional clause.
And it has two parts.
This part here is a predicate,..
condition, that's a condition.
The condition is expressed
by something called a predicate.
And a predicate in LISP
is some sort of thing
that returns either true or false.
And you see LISP has
a primitive procedure less than,
that tests
whether something is true or false.
And the other part of a clause
is an action or a thing to do
in the case where that's true.
And here what I'm doing is negating X.
The negation operator, well, the minus
sign in LISP is a little bit funny.
If there are two or more arguments...
if there are two arguments then it
subtracts the second one from the first.
We saw that. And if there's
one argument then it negates it.
So, this corresponds to that.
And there's another kind of clause. It
says in the case where X is equal to 0
the answer is zero.
And in the case where X is
greater than zero the answer is X.
Close that clause, close the cond,
close the definition.
There's a definition of absolute value
and you see that it's a case analysis
that looks very much like the
case analysis you use in mathematics.
OK. There's a somewhat different way
of writing a restricted case analysis.
Often you have a case analysis
where you only have one case.
Or you test something and
depending on whether
it's true or false you do something.
Here's another definition of absolute
value which looks almost the same,
which says if X is less then zero,
the result is negate X,
otherwise the answer is X.
We'll be using IF a lot. But again
the thing to remember is that this form
of absolute value
that you're looking at here
and then this one over here
that I wrote on the board
are essentially the same.
And IF and COND are
whichever way you like it.
You can think of COND
as syntactic sugar for IF,
or you can think of IF
as syntactic sugar for COND,
and it doesn't make any difference.
Person implementing
a LISP system will pick one
and implement the other in terms of that,
and it doesn't matter which one he pick.
OK. Why don't we break now
and then take some questions.
How come...
sometimes when I write define
I put an open paren here
and say define open paren
some thing or other,
and sometimes when I write this
I don't put an open paren?
OK. The answer is...
this particular form of define
where you say define some expression
is this very special thing
for defining procedures.
But again what it really means is I'm
defining this symbol square to be that.
So, the way you should think about it is
what define does is you write define
and then second thing you write
is this symbol here, no open paren,
this symbol you're defining.
And what you're defining it to be...
that's like here... and like here...
That's the sort of the
basic way you use define
and then there's
the special syntactic trick,
which allows you to define
procedures that look like this.
So, the difference is it's whether
or not you're defining a procedure.
Well, believe it or not,
you actually now know enough LISP
to write essentially
any numerical procedure,
that you'd write in a language
like Fortran or Basic or whatever,
well, essentially any other language.
You probably think
that's not believable, right?
Because you know that these languages
have things like for statements
and do...until/while or something.
But we don't really need any of that.
We're not gonna use
any of that in this course.
Let me show you
by again looking back at square root.
Let's go back to this
square root algorithm
of Heron of Alexandria.
Remember what that said?
It said to find an approximation to
the square root of X you make a guess,
you improve that guess by averaging
the guess and X over the guess,
you keep improving that
until the guess is good enough.
And I already alluded to the idea.
The idea is that
if the initial guess that she took...
if that initial guess was actually
equal to the square root of X,
then G here would be equal to X over G.
So if you hit the square root
averaging wouldn't change it.
IF the G that you pick was larger
than the square root of X
then X/G would be smaller
then the square root of X,
so that when you average G and X/G
you get something in between.
Right? So, if you pick a G that's too
small, your answer will be too large.
If you pick a G that's too large...
if the G is larger than the square
root of X then X/G will be smaller
than the square root of X.
So, averaging always
gives you something in between
and then it's not quite trivial
but it's possible to show that in fact
if G misses
the square root of X by a little bit
the average of G and X/G
will actually keep getting closer
to the square root of X.
So if you keep doing this enough
you'll eventually get as close
as you want and there's another fact
that you can always start out this
process by using 1 as an initial guess,
and it will always converge
to the square root of X.
Right? So, that is method of successive
averaging due to Heron of Alexandria.
Let's write it in LISP.
Well, the central idea is
what does it mean to try a guess
for the square root of X?
Let's write that. So we'll say
define...
to try a guess
for the square root of X...
What do we do?
We'll say if the guess is good enough...
If the guess is good enough
to be a guess for the square root of X,
then as an answer we'll take the guess.
Otherwise we will try the improved guess.
We'll improve that guess
for the square root of X
and will try that
as a guess for the square root of X.
... close the try,
close the if, close the define.
So, that's how we try a guess.
And then the next part of the process
said in order to compute square roots
we'll say define
to compute the square root of X
we will try 1 as a guess
for the square root of X.
Well, we have to define
a couple more things.
Well, we have to say how is a guess good
enough and how do we improve a guess.
So let's look at that.
The algorithm to improve the guess
Right? To improve a guess
for the square root of X we average...
That was the algorithm...
We average the guess
with the quotient of dividing X by the
guess. That's how we improve the guess.
And to tell whether a guess is good
enough for we have to decide something.
This is supposed to be a guess
for the square root of X.
So, one possible thing you can do
is say when you
take that guess and square it
do you get something very close to X?
For example one way to say that
is to say I square the guess,
subtract X from that and see if
the absolute value of that whole thing
is less than some small number,
which depends on my purposes.
OK. So, there's a...
there's a complete procedure
for how to compute the square root of X.
Let's look at
the structure of that a little bit.
I have the whole thing. I have the
notion of how to compute a square root.
That's some kind of module.
Right? That's some kind of black-box.
It's defined in terms of...
It's defined in terms of how to try
a guess for the square root of X.
Try is defined in terms of, well,
telling whether something is good enough
and telling how to improve something.
So, good enough...
Try is defined in terms of good-enough?
and improve.
And (let's see what else I'm filling)...
If you go down this tree
good-enough? was defined
in terms of absolute value and square.
And improve was defined
in terms of something called averaging
and then some other primitive operators.
Square root is defined in terms of try.
Try is defined in terms of good-enough?
and improve, but also try itself.
So try is also defined
in terms of how to try itself.
Well, that may give you some problem.
Your high school geometry teacher
probably told you that it's naughty
trying define things in terms of
themselves, cause it doesn't make sense.
But that's false.
Sometimes it makes perfect sense
to define things in terms of themselves.
And this is a case.
And we can look at that,
we can write down what this means
Let's say suppose I ask LISP
what the square root of 2 is.
Well, what does
the square root of 2 mean?
Well, that means I try 1
as a guess for the square root of 2.
Now, I look, I say gees, is 1 a good
enough guess for the square root of 2?
That depends on the test
that good-enough does.
And in this case
the good-enough will say no,
1 is not a good enough guess
for the square root of 2.
So, that will reduce to saying
I have to try
the improved and improved... improve 1
as a guess for the square root of 2
and try that as a guess
for the square root of 2.
Improving 1 as a guess for the square
root of 2 means I average 1 and 2/1.
So, this is gonna be the average...
this piece here will be the average
of 1 and the quotient of 2 by 1.
So, this piece here.
And I'm gonna try... And this is 1.5...
So, this square root of 2 reduces
to trying 1 for the square root of 2,
which reduces to trying 1.5
as a guess for the square root of 2.
Right? So that makes sense.
Let's look at the rest of the process.
Here, if I try 1.5, that reduces...
1.5 turns out to be not good enough
as a guess for the square root of 2.
So, that reduces to trying
the average of 1.5 and 2/1.5
as a guess for the square root of 2.
That average turns out to be 1.3333,
So, this whole thing reduces
to trying 1.3333 as a guess
for the square root of 2,and then so on.
Right? That reduces
to another call to good-enough.
1.4xxx and then it keeps going until the
process finally stops with something that
that good-enough thinks is good enough
which in this case is 1.4142xxx.
So, the process makes perfect sense.
This by the way
is called a recursive definition
And the ability to make
recursive definitions
is a source of incredible power.
I've hinted that it's the thing
that effectively allows you to do
these infinite computations that go on
until something is true.
Without having any other constructs other
than the ability to call a procedure.
Let's see there's one more thing
in this. Let me show you a variant
of this definition of square root.
Look here on this slide. Here is a...
Here's a sort of the same thing.
What I've done here is packaged
the definitions of improve and
good-enough and try inside square root.
So in fact what I've done
is I've built the square root box.
I've built a box that's this square root
procedure that someone can use.
They might put in 36 and get out 6.
And then packaged inside this box,
right, the definitions of try,
and good-enough, and improve.
So they're hidden inside this box
and the reason for doing that is that
if someone is using this square root...
if George is using this square root,
George probably doesn't care very much
that when I implemented square root
I had things inside there
called try and good-enough and improve.
And in fact, Harry
might have a cube root procedure
that has try and good-enough and improve
And in order to not get the whole system
confused it will be good for Harry
to package his internal procedures
inside his cube root procedure.
This is called block structure.
This particular way of packaging
internals inside of a definition.
And let's go back and look at this
slide again. The way to read this
this kind of procedure is
to say to define square root...
well, inside that definition
I'll have the definition of improve,
and the definition of good-enough,
and the definition of try.
And then subject to those definitions
the way I do square root is to try 1.
And notice here I don't have to say
1 as a guess for the square root of X.
Because since it's all inside this
square root it sort of has this X now.
OK. Well, let me summarize.
We started out with the idea
that what we're gonna be doing
is expressing imperative knowledge.
And in fact here's a slide that
summarizes the way we've looked at LISP.
We started out
by looking at some primitive elements:
addition, multiplication,
some predicates for testing whether
something is less than or something is equal
and in fact we saw really snickly
in the system we're actually using
these aren't actually primitives
but it doesn't matter.
What matters is we're gonna
use them as if they are primitives,
we're not gonna look inside.
We also have
some primitive data... some numbers.
We saw some means of composition, means
of combination, the basic one being
composing functions and building
combinations with operators and operands.
And there is some other things
like COND and IF and DEFINE.
But the main thing
about define in particular
was that it was the means of abstraction,
it was the way that we name things.
You can also see from this slide
not only where we've been
but holes we have to fill in.
At some point
we'll have to talk about how you combine
primitive data to get compound data,
and how you abstract data,
so you can use large clumps
of data as if they were primitive.
So, that's where we're going.
But before we do that for the next couple
of lectures we're gonna be talking about
first of all how it is that you make a
link between these procedures we write
and the processes
that happen in the machine.
And then how it is
that you start using the power of LISP
to talk not only about
these individual little computations
but about general
conventional methods of doing things.
OK. Are there any questions?
-Yes.If we'd defined A using parentheses
instead of as we did
what would be the difference?
-If I wrote this...
If I wrote that what I would be doing
is defining a procedure named A,
in this case a procedure of no arguments,
which when I ran it
would give me back 5 times 5.
- I mean you come over the same thing
except for you really got a difference.
- Right. And the difference...
the difference would be in the old one,
let me be a little bit clearer here...
Let's call this A like here.
And then pretend here just for contrast
I wrote define...
D to be the product of 5 and 5.
And the difference between those.
Let's think about interactions
with the LISP interpreter.
I would type in A
and LISP would return 25.
I could type in D...
if I just type in D, LISP would return
compound procedure D.
'Cause that's what it is,
it's a procedure.
I could run D. I could say
what's the value of running D?
Here is a combination with no operands.
And I see there are no operands.
I didn't put any after D.
And it would say Oh, that's 25.
Or I could say... just for completeness
if I typed in what's
the value of running A I get an error.
The error would be
the same one as over there.
The error would say sorry, 25,
which is the value of A, is not an
operator that I can apply to something.
OK.
Subtitles created by Sergey Khenkin
http://www.sicptitles.org